hi and welcome to this session on
analyzing performance issues with
profiling my name is Peter boring so
five releases ago in 2022 release way
one we launched the in client
performance profile a very powerful tool
for investigating performance issues
across extensions directly inside of the
web client since then profiling has
become essential to identify application
performance problems for customers
partners and support and is the main
performance troubleshooting tool used uh
today by
Partners so as a recap uh you open the
incline performance uh profile tool from
the help and support page there's a
troubleshooting section where you can
choose analyze performance or you can
also search for performance profiler in
the tel me so let's switch to the client
and see what happens then so here we now
see the inclined performance profile
that we had in the product for for quite
some releases and so the concept of the
incline performance profiler is that you
can uh start uh a recording you perform
your repost steps you stop and then you
inspect the results uh to try to
identify what could be slow and let's
try that out so to minimize the amount
of uh of content that you uh that you
record
it's recommendable to open the tool in a
new Pane and you can have them side by
side because then you can basically
navigate here uh in the product without
having uh you know before actually doing
the recording so here we now have the
two windows side by side so what was
slow was going to the customer list so I
will start the performance profiler uh I
will perform a rep steps in the UI which
was opening customers uh we can see that
it takes uh some time
and we wait until the result is done and
we can stop the performance profiler
let's just maximize the uh results here
so what the performance profile or
results is showing is the apps that take
part of the process that we captured so
in this case I had a profiler app and
you can see that it takes up to 5
Seconds uh to execute content in the
profiler app uh we can enable technical
information and in the technical
information uh we can scroll down and we
can see for example the time spent uh by
application object we see there's a page
extension in this app that takes almost
5 Second and we can even expand on the
call tree to see uh what is was actually
happening here and we see that the
unopen page in the page extension took
uh again almost uh 5 seconds so this
enabled us to understand um where time
is spent among the extensions and also
gives us some context about where to do
further investigation on a performance
uh issue for example uh I would probably
go and look at the on open page in this
page so one of the challenges with the
incline performance profiler that we
just saw is that capturing a performance
profile is interactive so either the
user that has a problem needs to capture
uh this profile and that likely involves
getting some help either by a customer
admin or maybe even from a consultant or
a support person could also be that a
consultant or support support personnel
must do this that requires that they
have access to the environment and
likely they still need to get in contact
with the user to get a concise rep uh uh
to be able to themselves reproduce the
issue and this is inefficient takes time
takes
collaboration also issues might be trans
Trent and hard to reproduce right maybe
even if they have the Repro stab it
doesn't repo that one time they do it
maybe it's something that happens during
the day on there certain special
scenarios that the user might not be
aware was part of the Repro steps also
the incline profile only supports
interactive user flows so that means
that you cannot profile web service
calls or background sessions like job
qes from within the
client to make it easier and faster for
customers Consultants developers
partners and support to capture a
profile and thereby lower manual
collaboration and time to mitigate this
release introduces schedule profiles so
with these you can capture performance
profiles automatically and
non-interactively in the background
based on well defined rules for when to
trigger the capture of a
profile the the rules that um you use to
to capture can then be set up by a
partner the user can just perform their
task during the day and then the partner
can come back later and analyze the
profiles afterwards to see if there's
any um obvious performance issues Trends
or something like that in the profiles
so this reduces the time spent on
collaboration and guidance and reduces
time to
mitigate and it also gives us the
ability to support both user actions but
also web service calls uh and background
tasks so just like with the inclined
performance profile you can invoke this
from help and support in a
troubleshooting section still there's a
new Option called analyze performance
with schedule profiler or you can again
search and tell me for profiler
schedules let's see how that works so
when you invoke that profile schedules
opens up and that gives you an overview
to manage all of your different
schedules for capturing profiles so
basically the different rule sets that
you defined uh on when you would like to
capture profiles in the background and
so in this case uh I just have two
already that I used uh prior to this
launch session but let's create a new
one so I I can invoke a new and that
opens up the profile schedule uh card
right and so um here I Define my
criteria for when I want to do a capture
so the first thing you have is that you
can enable or disable uh the the this
rule set right and I want to capture a
profile in a so I will keep this enabled
you can then Define a start and stop
time or start and end time for the
duration that you want to capture in by
default it suggests an hour from now and
I'm going to keep that because I just
want to do a short demo but in theory
you could have run it uh all day for
example and then come back and analyze
it depends a little bit on the
circumstances and how often the user is
running um the scenario or if it's a web
service call that you want to catch up
and profile Etc I can also do a um
description here and that's just you
know to have uniqueness in in the UI
here then I can select uh which user
that I want to run this for I want to
run it as myself uh and you can select
uh what type that you want to profile so
it can be activity in the browser if I'm
clicking around opening a customer card
or something like that it can also be
background tasks so job cues or web
service course that I want to uh trigger
on like for the existing profiling uh
scenarios you can set the sampling
frequency that's basically um how often
we look at what is going on as part of
profiling you can set the activity
duration threshold that's basically uh
how small uh or how slow should things
be H before we start profiling it right
and I'll I'll set that to 100 a little
lower and you can also set the retention
period because we save these profiles uh
on the um NST or the service and after
some certain time they will be deleted
and and you can invoke that as well or
set that as well so now we have that
live and so basically what we would do
this is monitoring me and my activities
so I'm just going to go out of profile
schedules uh I'm just going to go and um
actually rerun uh this customers page
that I
had and because that's the scenario that
was a little bit slow
and we see it slow now as well and just
for the sake of the demo itself let's
open up a card we can also just in sales
go to some items just to do a little
thing different things right that could
mimic how a user could use this during
the day so now we want to look at the
results uh there's different ways that
you can do that you can either open uh
performance profiles page H that will
basically just open uh up all all of the
capture profiles not just for this
schedule or this set of rules but for
everything so um if you want to have it
filtered to a specific task or specific
schedule it's actually better to go in
and look at the the specific uh profiler
schedule that we set up before so I
defined this PC live uh schedule and
there you have an action for opening the
profiles that was captured and then
they're filtered just to this schedule
and we see that I performed opening the
customer list uh and also the item list
here going into the actual card was
actually too fast to be noticed and we
see that we have some slowness in in
these scenarios and again we can drill
into then the profile like before and
it's the exact same result that we see
now again uh the something is really
slow in the profile extension I can go
into the technical information and I can
drill down and I can again see things
like the call tree and understand what
is taking all of the time and we see
again that this unopen page takes almost
5 Seconds right so this is a way of
using background
profiling so what should you do well
first of all if you haven't already
tried it out use the existing profiling
features that we have in client that I
showed in the beginning but also the
ability to profile from within Vis
Studio code if you are a developer then
use the new capability of scheduling
profile captures so that they can run in
the background this is mainly targeting
consultants and
support um you can go to
aka.ms BBC troubleshooting and read more
about this tool as well as the other
tools that we have to help you in
troubleshooting customer
cases um we have also some documentation
for this um and these links will be in
the description uh for this session as
well and also we have a related feature
because we saw before in the performance
profile that it looked like there was a
problem in the unopen page but maybe you
want to go and investigate that code and
a couple of releases ago we actually
made it very simple fast to go from the
web client into Visual Studio code and
look at code for the functionality that
you viewing and we call that opening Vis
Studio code and you can learn more about
that if you look at the um launch events
sessions from last year uh and we'll
provide a link in the description as
well for
this thank you for joining